1401大型机演示
计算机历史博物馆
加利福尼亚州山景城
2015年10月14日
听译/校对：某科学的小姚同志
本片由Ken Ross提供
My name is Ken Ross and I'm the lead demo or today
我是主导今天演示的Ken Ross
and this is...this is Paul Lawton
这一位是Paul Lawton
and he's the today he's my assistant,sometimes I'm his assistant,
他今天是我的助手 有时我也是他的助手
but you want to say a few words about yourself.
先让他来讲述一下自己的故事吧
Sure,my name is Paul Lawton
好的 我叫Paul Lawton
and in 1965 I was attending Virginia Tech.
在1965年时 我进入弗吉尼亚理工大学学习
At Virginia Tech I took the only course they had in computer programming.
在那里我选修了唯一的一门计算机编程课
It was a course in Fortran.
那门课程教的是Fortran语言
【Fortran是Formula Translation的缩写，数值计算的功能较强】
After I did that I decided my career was going to be in computer programming.
从此我选择了计算机编程的生涯
So I spent my entire career in computer programming,
之后我一直在干程序员这一行
work for great companies like IBM,Apple,Logitech,Atari,
期间效力于IBM、苹果、罗技、雅达利等多家公司
and I'm retired.Now I'm here telling you how much fun I had my career.
现在我退休了 在这里为大家分享我工作之中的乐趣
Okay.
好的
So before we start that you know welcome to that Computer History Museum 1401 demo.
开始演示之前 欢迎大家参观计算机历史博物馆的1401展区
【“计算机历史博物馆”（Computer History Museum）位于美国硅谷】
The 1401 was actually introduced in 1959 and it's been known maybe as the Model T Ford of computers.
1401计算机在1959年发布  被誉为计算机界的“福特T系列汽车”
【福特T系列汽车是世界上第一种批量生产的汽车】
By 1965 over half the computers in the world were IBM family 1401s.
到1965年 世界上超过半数的计算机都是IBM家族的1401大型机
By the end of the 1960s,there were about fifteen thousand of them in use.
20世纪60年代末时 大概有五万台这样的机器在工作
But before we start the demo,I'd like to take you back in time.
开始演示之前 我想带你回顾一下历史
Back to the summer of 1962,JFK was president and the Cold War was the hot topic on the news.
1962年夏天 肯尼迪总统当政 美苏冷战还是热点新闻
I had just finished my freshman year at MIT,
我在麻省理工学院读完大一
and it secured a summer programming job at a mid-size department store chain in Detroit Michigan.
获得了一份为密歇根州底特律一家中等规模连锁商场编程的暑期工作
Company was called Federal Department Stores,
那家公司叫“联邦百货商店”
and Federal's had just installed two state-of-the-art 1401, very similar to these.
他们刚刚安装了两台先进的1401计算机 和你面前的是这些一样的
And there are two machines in this room.
一间房子里有两台机器
And they were going to use the computers to do basic accounting tasks,
他们使用计算机做一些基础的财会工作
like inventory control,payroll,sales analysis.
比如说库存管理，工资清单还有销售分析
And that's the way computers were used in the early 1960s.
这正是20世纪60年代早期计算机的用武之地
There was no interaction,online ordering,anything like that.
那时还没有网上交流，在线购物之类的应用
It was all tabulating basic information.
计算机只能承担基本信息的制表工作
In the room I worked in was very similar to this.
我工作的那间机房和这间很相似
This represents a computer room from the 1960s.
这就是一个典型的上世纪60年代的机房
You can hear the loud air-conditioning because these computers put out a lot of heat.
计算机发热量很大 空调声振耳欲聋
You're standing on a raised floor,
你站在这种高架地板上
【高架地板就是现代机房中使用的架空防静电地板，下部形成的空间用于走线】
and we'll explain and show you why.
我一会儿再向你解释原因
And I guess there's a little bit of smell of oil
或许还充斥着一点机油味
because all these machines are very mechanical as well as electronic.
这是因为所有这些机器都是机电一体化产品
So in the middle of the room that I work for two 1401s,you know,
在房间的中部我操作着两台1401计算机
this is the Card Reader-Card Puncher.
如你所见 这是穿孔卡片阅读-打孔机
【译者注：这里讲解员用手拍的是卡片分类机，不是穿孔卡片阅读-打孔机；穿孔卡片阅读-打孔机是打印机左侧的那台】
This is the way information gets into the machine.
信息通过它输入到计算机中
This is the CPU here you have a...CPU here.
这是中央处理单元（CPU）
...the control panel and we actually interact with these machines physically back in those days,
上面有控制面板 当年我们一般通过物理方式和计算机交互
【“物理方式”指按钮、开关和指示灯】
not like we do today.
和现在（通过软件）大不相同
We have all these switches.
这里全都是开关
This is the 1403 printer.
这个是1403型打印机
And it was the most advanced printer of its time
它在当时是最先进的打印机了
and we're going to be showing you that.
我们稍后将为你展示
And last but not least are these 729 tape drives.
这几台IBM 729磁带机也很重要
【IBM早期磁带机使用“7轨磁带”，其中6个轨道用于数据记录，1个轨道用于奇偶校验】
【磁带机是高速外围设备，而卡片阅读-打孔机是低速外围设备，两种设备都可以作为输入/输出设备，信息可以在其间互传】
And again we're going to be demoing all these and telling you more about them.
等会儿我们再演示并作详细介绍
Oop...he just started them up.
唔 他把它们启动了
Emm...but the...in addition...in addition to just a computer,
因此我们看到这台计算机本身
there were a lot of other machines that were really needed to run job.
需要外围许多其他机器的辅助才能正常工作
So it went into the room where I worked there were about 20 key bunch machines that are like these.
走进我工作的房间 有二十台像这样的键盘卡片打孔机
Er...women were sitting them with stacks of paper.
呃 女打字员拿着成叠的纸张坐在机器前
They would be timesheets,sales tickets or inventory control tags.
纸张通常是工时单，销售发票或者库存管理标签
And of course back in the early 1960s,
当然在上世纪60年代早期
women did basically all of the key punching.
键盘打孔的工作通常都是由女性完成的
【这是因为键盘打孔的工作需要细心和耐心】
In addition to that key punching,there's these other ancillary machines.
除了键盘打孔机外 还有一些别的辅助设备
【“制表机”和“穿孔卡片”相伴而生，由霍尔瑞斯发明，用于解决人口普查问题】
【穿孔卡片类似于今天的“机读卡”，一张穿孔卡片对应一个人，分栏记录其多种信息】
【制表机最重要的功能就是对卡片各栏各选项的计数功能，这是人口普查中最核心的工作】
So we have the unit record equipment you want to that...that would...
以更早的单元记录设备为例……
【“单元记录设备”是改良的制表机，包括了卡片打孔器、阅读器和分类器，是IBM 1401计算机的祖先】
【“制表机”和“单元记录设备”促成了IBM公司的成立，详情请见风车大大的AV12020182，AV14727420和AV14941579】
You need to collate,sort,tabulate,interpret
我们还需要完成整理、分类、打孔制表和翻译等其他工作
【“翻译”是指将统计结果转换为方便人们阅读的形式】
and they were run to put these plug boards
完成这些需要这个叫插接版的东西
or the programs for this unit record equipment.
上面就是单元记录设备的“程序”
【这里的“程序”是通过硬连线实现的组合逻辑，用来使机器适应不同的统计任务】
Emm...these...this is a program I...I don't have any idea what it does,
呃 这上面就有个“程序” 但我不知道是做什么用的
but it would typically read an 80 column punch card
但一般都是用来读取80栏穿孔卡片
and might tabulate a field of numbers it might print or interpret or do something like that.
或许还可以完成统计出一些数字然后将它们打印或翻译出来这类的工作
【IBM研发1401的目的就是取代单元记录设备，实现数据处理的进一步电子化】
So...so the program library before our computer was racks full of these cards.
因此 我们计算机前的“程序库”其实就是放满了这些卡的架子
My favorite machine which...which we used a lot of which is the...(Someone interrupts)
我们经常使用的机器里我最喜欢的一台是……（这里有人打断了讲话）
So that when you're processing punch cards everything needed to be sorted.
话说回来 当你处理穿孔卡片上的数据之前需要先对卡片进行分类
If you're doing payroll you typically sort by social security number or Department.
当处理工资清单时 通常是依据社会保障号码或部门进行分类
【社会保障号码是美国人出生时得到的正式身份号码】
If you're doing sales analysis you might sort by product ID.
当做销售分析时 可能就根据产品序列号进行分类
And we all got very familiar with the process of sorting cards.
我们对卡片分类的过程都非常熟悉了
Ken:Paul you want... Paul:to sort first? Ken:Huh...
Ken：Paul你来…… Paul：先来演示一下分类吗？ Ken：呃……
Paul:Got a sort? Ken:Sort!
Paul：分下类吗？ Ken：好，分类！
So basically this machine can sort on one column of an 80 column card.
这台机器基本上是依据80栏穿孔卡片中的某一栏进行分类的
And there's a little setting here to tell us which column we're going to sort on.
这儿有个用来设置的小东西 可以选择依据哪一栏来分类
So it reads the information in the column and pumps it into the appropriate a slot here.
机器可以读取选中那一栏的内容并根据它将卡片送到相应的槽中
【好比如今的光电机读答题卡，比如选中的栏为第14题，分类机分别将第14题选中A、B、C、D的卡送到四个对应的卡槽里】
So,here we go!
现在可以开始了！
So you can see it's reading them and dropping them into the proper sort.
可以观察到机器会读取卡片信息并将它们送到相应的分类中
It's doing that at a thousand cards a minute.
分类的速度是每分钟1000张卡片
Now back in the year when this machine was used,
回想这台机器被使用的那个年代
there might be...Oh,let's say you're doing some security numbers.
或许是……就以处理社会保险帐号为例
Now,since you're doing one column at a time,
由于机器一次只能处理一栏
how many sorts would that take?
请问需要分类几次呢？
Nine... right?
是九次，对吗？
【美国的社会保险账号有九位数】
Now suppose you were the IRS and you had 200 million customers,
现在假设你是有两亿名客户的美国国家税务局
and you had to sort it on all the social security numbers.
你需要根据社会保险账号对客户的卡片进行分类
You can imagine how many machines it would take, how many people would take.
不难想象出需要占用多少台机器 雇佣多少人才能完成这个工作
That was really full employment back in the day.
这在当年绝对要耗费不少人力资源
Now,once you sort on one column, in order to maintain the sort,
这台机器帮你分好了一栏 为了继续进行二次分类
you have to take these cards out in a very special way.
你需要用一种特殊的方式取出这些卡片
And I've got this sort and if I wanted to do the next column,
本次分类就完成了 如果你想分类下一栏
I'd move the pointer over and sort them again.
我需要移动这个游标并重新分类
We're not going to do that but that's the way it works.
接下来的工作是类似的 我就不演示了
Okay.
好的 感谢
So yeah,we all got very familiar with managing large decks of cards.
现在大家都应该对管理海量卡片的方法非常熟悉了
And for those of you that are programmers,
然而对于程序员来说
programmers were written on these decks of cards.
程序员的工作就是编写这海量的卡片
How many of your programmers in this room? Okay.
在场有多少朋友是程序员？好
So if you were a good programmer,I was,but sure Paul,emm...
如果你是一名像我和Paul这样的还不错的程序员
that you'd make sure you kept sequence numbers in the last five columns of the cards
你就应该保证卡片的最后五栏是卡片的顺序编号
in case the deck got dropped,
万一不小心打翻了桌子
and you need to sort your program back into the original sequence.
就能通过分类排序使程序卡片恢复原来的顺序
So just continuing on with a narrative IBM actually began the development of the 1401 in 1957.
传奇的IBM实际上在1957年就开始1401机的研发工作了
The goal was to create an entry level machine that rented for about $2,500 a month.
他们的目标是推出一台每月租金2500美元的入门级机器
That's about $15,000 a month in today's dollars.
放在今天大概是每月15000美元
And the reason for the $2,500 a month is that
之所以每月会产生2500美元的租金
it was sort of the average that people used to pay
我这里说的是客户支付的平均价格
to rent all these old card accounting machines.
租下这些老爷卡片财务机器
Emm..the...for the rental price.
没错 是租赁的价格
And people rented the computers back then,
是因为那时人们仅仅租下计算机
they didn't really buy them.
而没有将它们买下来
You had your IBM reps.You had a month-to-month bill.
每个公司会配有IBM的推销员 公司的账单是按月结算的
You could...you could upgrade your computer.
你可以选择升级计算机
You could downgrade your computer,
也可以选择降级计算机
if you...if you decided that you wanted a hardware multiply/divide
有时候你还需要硬件乘法/除法器
which happens to be an option on this machine.
这在这台机器上是选装配件
You call up your IBM rep.They bring out a few of these cards then put them in.
这时你可以给你的IBM推销员打电话 他们就会派人送来这些扩展卡并帮你装上
And lo and behold,your monthly bill would go up by a few hundred bucks a month.
你瞧 你的每月账单就会增加几百美元
So IBM was actually able to achieve the cost and reliability goals
IBM取得了高收益不说 用户还会觉得它非常可靠
by incorporating the solid-state modules you want...
依靠这种加装你需要的晶体管模块的服务
These...these solid-state cards...pass these around here...emm...
这就是晶体管扩展卡 大家可以传着看看
Each of these...each of these cards has a few transistors on it.
每一张卡上只有几个晶体管
I'm not an engineer.
我不是工程师
This card has...it looks like six transistors.
这张卡看上去……好像有六个晶体管
There's about 3,000 of these things in each 1401.
在每台1401机里有大概3000个这种东西
And as you're well aware,a modern chip would have a billion transistors in it or probably more.
和你想的一样 一片现代芯片里有十亿或更多个晶体管
So this wasn't very advanced but the machines were very reliable.
因此这台机器不是非常先进 但却无比可靠
Amazingly,so in here you want to...
很让人惊奇不是吗？
In addition to the solid-state cards,
除了这些晶体管卡之外
IBM incorporated and as I said earlier state-of-the-art 1403 printer.
IBM还提供了我之前说的先进的1403打印机服务
And we're going to demos...demonstrate later,
我们打算稍后展示
why this was the most advanced printer on the market.
并为大家解释为什么是当时业界最先进的
But just take my word for it that it was.
大家对这一点有个印象就可以了
Now,IBM shipped the first 1401 the Time Life in 1960.
在1960年 IBM把第一台第一台1401机卖给了Time Life
【Time Life是时代公司Time Inc.旗下的子公司，《时代周刊》（Time）的缔造者】
【1990年该公司随其直属母公司Direct Holdings Global LLC交由时代华纳Time-Warner公司管理】
And at that time,time life had 40 million punch cards,
在那时 Time Life有四千万张穿孔卡片
40 million punchcards that it used to keep track of its accounting information and its mailing with information.
四千万张穿孔卡片都被用作保存记账信息和联络信息了
And to give you a sense for that forty million,
为了让你对这四千万张穿孔卡片产生一个直观印象
this standard box of punch cards is two thousand cards.
这个标准的存放穿孔卡片的纸盒里有两千张卡片
So 40 million punch cards is about twenty thousand boxes of cards
因此四千万张穿孔卡片要装满两万个这种盒子
which actually I computed to be a stack about seven miles high.
叠放起来我计算了下需要七英里（约合11.27千米）
So it's a lot of...a lot of punch cards.
这实在是有很多穿孔卡片了
Now with the advent of magnetic tape like this,
在这种磁带发明以后
it really changed the way companies could process larger volumes of data.
公司存储海量数据的方式也随之改变
This reel of magnetic tape contains...can contain about between 50,000 and 200,000 cards.
这一卷磁带能存储大概五万到二十万张穿孔卡片的信息
So Time Life's entire inventory of information could be contained on a couple of hundred reels of tape。
也就是说Time Life公司的全部库存信息可以放在几百卷磁带中
But of course,in addition to the couple of hundred reels of tape,
当然除了这几百卷磁带以外
you probably needed another couple of hundred reels of tape as backup probably off-site.
或许还需要另外几百卷磁带作为异地备份
Now,if you think about it,we have...we have 40 million punch cards,
想象一下 我们有四千万张穿孔卡片
each card has 80 characters of information on it.
每张卡片能存放80个字符的信息
And your put your good mathematician,
运用一下你的数学思维
how many total characters of information is that represent?
那意味着总共多少字符的数据呢？
A few gigabytes.
几个GB
A few gigabytes.It's actually 3.2 gigabytes.
是几个GB 准确地说是3.2GB
So you can store all of that information on this actually...obsolete four gigabyte thumb drive.
现在你用一个这样的过时4GB U盘就能够存储这所有信息
And it really illustrates the way Moore's Law has come...has applied the storage as well as computation.
这再次印证了摩尔定律在存储容量和计算力上的预测生效了
【摩尔定律：当价格不变时，集成电路上可容纳的元器件的数目，约每隔18-24个月便会增加一倍，性能也将提升一倍】
Emm,and last before we actually get into running with the the programs,
最后在我们进行程序运行演示之前
I'd like to talk about the processor a little bit.
我还想简单谈一谈这台机器的处理器
So the 1401 stored information in BCD,
1401机器是利用BCD码存储信息的
Binary Coded Decimal,character by character.
也就是逐字用二进制编码表示的十进制
【BCD码是用二进制来表示十进制的一种编码，4个二进制位表示一个十六进制数，但只有0-9有效，A-F无效】
【BCD码运算后结果超出了9，需要调整才能修正为正确的BCD码，经典8086处理器就有相关的汇编指令如DAA和DAS】
Each character position has six bits of information.
我们用六个二进制位表示一个字
【一个“字”表示键盘卡片打孔机上的一个键】
【六个二进制位指A B 8 4 2 1；A与B无效时8 4 2 1表示数字；A和B有效时表示键盘分区，结合8 4 2 1的组合表示大写字母】
So there are no lower case,just upper case.
因此没有小写字母 只有大写字母
One word mark bit and one parity bit.
除此之外还有一个字标记位和一个奇偶校验位
【1的个数为奇数称之为奇校验，反之为偶校验】
And information was stored in variable length fields.
信息以可变长度的形式存储
So if you wanted to store a 20 digit number,
也就是说如果想要存储一个20位的数字
You could store a 20 digit number and it was delimited by the word mark bit.
你可以直接连续存放这20个数字 并在后面跟一个字标记位表示数据的终结
So,you know,if you would address the low-order position
如果你想寻址数据的低位字节
and the computer would read forward until it in a word mark.
计算机会持续读取数据 直到遇到了字标记位才会停下来
So that's a lot different than a modern computer which would have a 64-bit register.
这与具有64位寄存器的现代计算机有着很大的不同
You can store 200 character strings,20 character numbers...
你可以一次性存放具有200字的字符串 也可以存放只有20位的数字
The cycle time on this machine is 87,000,right,87k cycle time.
机器的时钟速度是每秒87000个机器周期
And to add two ten digit numbers took about a half of a millisecond.
将两个十位数相加耗费约0.5毫秒
The other thing that's important as information was stored in core memory.
另一个重要的信息点是信息存储在磁芯存储器中
【磁芯存储器作为机器的内存】
So...you wanna...you want...you got that one.
所以……你来展示那一个
So...core memory are little teeny donuts...magnetic iron donuts, with an X two wires that go between.
所谓磁芯存储的关键是这些有磁性的小圆环 中间有两条X状交叉的导线穿过
【这些小磁环组成阵列，每个磁环用不同的内磁场方向表示1或0；环状使其不能形成裸露的磁极，防止相互干扰】
【磁环的磁滞曲线是方形的，较小的电流就可以为其充磁，且磁性不易失去】
【磁环45度斜放，两条导线成十字或X状穿过磁环，用于寻址磁环并改变磁环中的磁场方向】
【两线中的各一半的电流产生的磁场矢量叠加恰能磁化小磁环，电流方向决定磁化方向；这种方法被称为“电流重合法”】
【另有一条检测线蛇形穿过所有磁环，检测数据时利用十字线寻址并加已知方向的电流】
【根据磁环中磁场方向的不同，使得磁环磁感应强度发生或不发生突变，从而在感应线中产生或不产生感应电流】
【这种通过写入来得到感应电流读取数据的方式会破坏数据本身，因此读取完成后要立刻回写】
【有时还会有一条禁止线蛇形穿过所有磁环，禁止线通入一定的电流，抵消一部分交叉写入线产生的磁场，使得无法写入】
And this is just a representation...my hands here...
描述起来就是这样……这个先给我……
Emm...this box here actually has eight character...has 140 characters of core memory on it.
嗯……这个小盒子里面的磁芯有8个字……能存储140个字
It's actually one tweet of memory.
这恰好是（早期）推特上一篇推文的字数限制
And this little vial has hundreds of these little ferrite cores in it.
这个小瓶子里有数百个这样的微小铁氧体磁环
【磁芯存储器在失去电源后数据不会丢失，较为可靠，写入快而读取慢，功率和产热都比较大】
And I'll pass this around,you guys maybe can pass this around.
我会把这个传下去 你们可以传着看一看
Interestingly enough,core memory back then was very expensive.
有意思的是 磁芯存储器在当时非常昂贵
A character...a byte,I'll use the term although byte wasn't used back then.
一个字……或者说一个字节 虽然当时没有字节这个单位
【一个字节是八个二进制位，之所以用它来描述一个字是因为英语中所有字母连同数字都可以表示为一个字节的ASCII码】
Character would cost five dollars.
存储一个字要花费5美元
Today,that's $30...there right yes,today is $30.
换算成今天要花30美元……没错 就是30美元（约合210元）
Okay I have a new 64 gigabyte iPhone.
现在我有一台64G的iPhone手机
Let's say 64 gigabytes times $30,
让我们算一算 64G乘每字节30美元
about 1.8 trillion dollars of memory if I do back on to do the translation.
换算在当时要用1.8万亿美元
So,let's see...I think that's really all for the processor.
让我想想……关于处理器的内容就介绍完了
【IBM 1401有自己的“指令集”，其“汇编语言”称作“字符串处理系统”即Symbolic Programming System】
I think we're ready to do a demo.
我觉得我们可以做演示了
Where is that little core memory you have? This one?
那个磁芯存储器放哪儿了？是这个吗？
That was a little...
那有点儿……
Oh...hey...the box? The tweet?
哦……嘿！是那个盒子？那个“一个推特”的盒子？
The little box yeah.
是那个没错
Black one,yeah?
黑色的吗？
Yep!
是的！
Don't let it...where is that?
别让它……刚才传到哪儿了？
Here,he's got it.
哦 在他那儿
Hold that up for a second,just this little one here.Let me hold it.
请把它举起来一会儿 就是那个小的 还是给我吧
This has a hundred and forty characters...of core memory,those little teeny cores.
这个磁芯存储器能存储140个字符 里面都是小磁环
It was used as a print buffer.
它被用作打印缓冲区
Anybody know what 140 characters is today?
有人知道140个字在今天相当于什么吗？
One tweet！
是一篇推特的推文！
So we have here in my hand one tweet of old memory.
所以我手里拿的是能存储一片推文的古老存储器
Okay,last but not least,because,I need you Paul.
好的 最后我需要Paul你来帮我
This is a USB cable.Everybody see the USB cable.
这是一条USB数据线 大家应该都能看到
You want to show them a USB cable from 1962?
你来给大家展示一下1962年的“USB数据线”吧？
Take this and pass it around.
接好了 大家传看一下
Yeah we're not worried about anybody walking off with that.
我们并不用担心有人会把它顺走
I think it weighs about 10 pounds.
我想它大概有10磅重（约合4.5千克）
You can take it if you can.
你要拿得动就接着
Okay,you want to grab a volunteer?
好的 你需要找一名志愿者吗？
Okay,we'll basically what we're going to do next is demonstrate the key punch.
我们接下来要演示键盘卡片穿孔的工作
And in the spirit of the era that we're in the 1960s,women did all the key punching.
在20世纪60年代那个时期 键盘卡片打孔的工作都是由女士来完成的
So I'd like a woman volunteer to come up and help me demonstrate.
所以我想请以为女士来当志愿者 帮助我完成接下来的演示
And...Ha ha ha! You are our volunteer.Come on in.
呃……哈哈哈……你就是天选之子！请进来吧！
Well,we'll teach you.
别紧张 我们会教你做的
Walk over to have a seat in this chair over here.
请走到这里来 坐在这个椅子上
Okay,now up here we have a bunch of blank cards.
现在机器里面装好了一叠空白卡片
And what we need to do is we need to feed it down into the punch station.
我们需要将它输送下来进入穿孔台中
So there's a key called "feed".
这儿有个写着“输送(feed)”的按键
So you press the "feed" key.
请按一下“输送”键
Okay.Now it's down here but we still need to register it into the punch station.
好 现在卡片已经下来了 但我们还要将它卡入穿孔台中
So hit "register".
现在按一下“记录(register)”键
Now,what I'd like you to do is type "Your First Name space Last Name".
现在请你输入“‘你的名字’空格‘你的姓氏’”
It's all upper case and don't make a mistake.
它们全都是大写字母 小心别出错
There's no backspace key on a key punch.
在键盘卡片穿孔机上没有退格键
I'm sorry?
对不起 我没有听清
Is it's all upper case there?
上面全是大写字母吗？
Oh,it's all upper case.
是的 全都是大写字母
There is no lower case.
上面没有小写字母
There's only 42 possible characters that you can punch.
只有42种可用的字符以供穿孔
Did you punch your First Name space Last...Okay.
打好“你的名字 姓氏”……好的
So now we hit "release".
现在我们按一下“释放(release)”键
Now remember I said don't make a mistake?
还记得我说过不要犯错吗？
Let's suppose you got out to column 51 and you made a mistake.
现在我们假设你在第51栏打错了一个字母
Well,you got two choices.
现在你有两种选择
You can either redo the whole card or you can duplicate what you've already done.
要么选择重做整张卡片 要么选择复制完成无误的部分
So let's simulate that.
我们来模拟一下这种情形
So hit the "feed" key again and hit the "register" key-"REG".
先按“输送”键 再按“记录”键 就是“REG”键
Now hold down the "duplicate".
现在按住“复制(duplicate)”键
So what we're doing is we're reading from here and punching over here.
现在机器或从这里读取信息 再向这边打孔
Now if you had made a mistake in column 51,
如果你在第51栏犯了个错误
you could duplicate all the way out to call them 50 and then continue to type.
你就一直复制到第50栏 然后继续输入就行了
So we're done.
这就完成了
So hit "release"-"register"-"release" and "register".
现在按“释放”-“记录”-“释放” 再按一下“记录”键
One thing I'll say is after we finish the demo,
我想告诉大家在我们完成演示之后
we stay around and anybody that wants to punch their name in a card,
我们会一直呆在这里 如果有人想要在卡片上打上自己的名字
and we're going to run the "Big Print" program to print out...you can do it.
然后运行“大号字体打印”程序打印出来 也可以自己来尝试一下
So,now we've given you a demonstration how this works.
我们已经向大家展示了它的工作流程
You've proved yourself competent.
恭喜你证明了自己是能胜任这个工作的
So you can go down to our personnel department,
所以你现在可以去我们的人事部门
get a job for 80 cents an hour.
领取一份每小时80美分的工作
【当年80美分折合于当年的2元人民币；1960年一个中国家庭一个月大概是60-80元人民币的收入】
【1960年的1元钱，能买到将近2斤的猪肉，约10斤白菜，10斤大米，30根冰棍，甚至还可以下馆子吃一顿丰盛的大餐】
And here you go,Betsy.
非常感谢你 Betsy！
And I'm going to keep this for a little while.
这张卡片我会保留一会儿再给你
You're gonna go...run "Big Print"... Right now?
你准备运行“大号字体打印”程序……是现在吗？
Emm...now? Yeah,sure!
现在？没错 就是现在！
Okay,we're going to move down this way
我们把视线移动到这边
because we're going to now be running on the German machine
接下来的我们要启动这台德国产的机器
which is the one that's actually operational today.
它至今仍然能够正常运行
Yep...yeah,you got the(I can't hear clearly,sorry)...Okay.
是的 你到……好吧
So you...you can watch the cards go in and watch them pop out there.
这样你可以观察到卡片进入再弹出到这儿的过程
Hold on a second but...
你先稍等一下……
Are you ready? Okay we're ready.
你准备好了吗？我准备好了
Before I do this,I want to tell you a little bit about this...this machine.
在操作之前 我想向你补充这台机器的一些信息
Basically this is the software.This is a program.
基本上说这就是软件 它就是程序
And this is the only way of getting programs or data in is through this card reader.
卡片阅读机是计算机获取程序和数据的唯一渠道
Now there's no operating system in this machine.
这台计算机没有操作系统
So everything that a program needs has to be in this deck.
因此程序所需的一切都必须放在这一叠卡片中
Now when I press the load key,it's going to read this first card in,
当我按下“载入”键时 机器会读入第一张卡片上的信息
just the first card and it's going to transfer to the instructions on this card.
并只将第一张卡片上包含的指令传输过去
It's called a bootstrapped card.
这张卡片被称为“启动自举”卡
The bootstrapped card has to be responsible for reading in the rest of the program.
“启动卡”要负责读取剩下的程序
So basically...put the cards into the reader.
我们把卡片放入阅读机
And we have this weight to weigh the cards down so they'll feed better.
然后放上配重片将卡片压紧 这让卡片更容易送入
Then press a couple of buttons.
然后按几个按键
And then I'm going to hit the load key.
最后我按下“载入”键
And you can see it's reading the cards in and dropping them into a slot there.
之后你能看到机器在读卡 卡片会落入这里的槽中
Now it's read the data card.
现在数据卡片也被读取了
Yeah...copper wire...(I can't identify what they are talking about)
是……铜质导线……
I don't know the answer to that but yeah...but...I can get...
我无法解答这个问题但我能找……
Somebody will be here and I'll get the answer for you.
一会儿会有人来为你解答这个问题
Okay,so that's...that's the "Big Print",you know.
这就是“大号字体打印”程序的效果
Reading the cards in...
读入卡片……
We want to talk a little bit about the printer now.
我们现在稍微深入讲解一下打印机
I show everybody what we did here.
刚才的演示大家也看见了
We took Betsy's card with a "First Name Last Name" and print it in a big letter(s).
我们拿到Betsy的记录有“名字 姓氏”的卡片 将上面的内容用大号字母打印了出来
Thus it's called "Big Print".
因此它被叫做“大号字体打印”程序
So,Betsy.
给你 Betsy
So we said it...we said earlier that this was the most advanced printer on the market
我们之前提到过这是业界最先进的打印机
And I'd like to explain why.You want to hold...Oh,yep.
我现在解释一下原因 你帮我拿一下……哦 是的
So all of the other printers in their early 60s were configured
在60年代早期其他的打印机都大同小异
so that each print position there might be a spinning wheel with a character set
它们通过一个刻有各种字符的转轮来实现打印位置的移动
or little arms that might have gone up and down.
再者就是利用上下移动的小机械臂
But the result of that is that the printer...
这么做的结果就是打印机……
the printing that you saw from a computer was wavy.It was really awkward.
计算机打印的结果是起伏不平的 这有点难办
IBM developed the 1403 with this horizontal print chain.
IBM发明了1403型打印机 它装配有这种“水平打印链条”
You want to hold it up...yup...
麻烦你把它举起来给大家展示一下
So that...that chain spins at 90 inches a second.
每秒链条会转过90英寸（约2.3米）
It's got five copies of the character string.
也就是可以得到五份完整的字符串拷贝
And as you'll see and as you can see,the printing is very high-quality.
正如你所见 打印的质量很高
It's very level.
字符都在一条水平线上
And,you know,it was very good for printing forms,paychecks and things like that.
这对于打印表格 薪水支票一类的东西来说是再好不过的了
We're about to crash...let's say...
在以往我们会搞砸……怎么说呢……
You want to...you want to crank up powers.
你要提高功率吗？
So...so you know and one of the experiences I remember of it
我和你们分享一些我记忆中那时的经历
is it had to do with designing a paycheck form,writing the program,
我先要设计薪水支票表格 之后再写程序
ordering like thousands of pre-printed forms that's four-part carbon paper
然后采购数千份预先打印好的表格 那都是有四联的复写纸
and worrying that my program wasn't going to align correctly with the printer.
最后还要担心我写的程序能不能在打印机上正确对齐
Or when I'm loading the checks into the printer, there's a process to get them aligned.
当我把支票放进打印机时 有个把它们对正的流程
And you push the button and it starts printing lots of checks.
按下按钮 机器开始打印大量的支票
And what if you've done it wrong,you print 10,000 paychecks that are not aligned right.
如果你做错了 就会得到一万张文字没有对齐的薪水支票
So...Paul...Paul is going to run a program that's going to really compute powers of two.
现在Paul运行了一个计算2的幂次的程序
It's just going to exercise the printer but it's good.
这很是考验打印机 但它还吃得消
I've lifted the sound cover on this so that you can hear the full beauty of the printer.
我抬起隔音罩以便大家更好地感受这台打印机的美
But in reality,I'm going to put it back down now.
但在现实生产中 我还是要把它放下来的
Still makes a lot of noise.
哪怕是这样噪音都很大
So when you were working in a computer room in the 1960s,
如果你在一个20世纪60年代的机房里工作的话
you know,two or three printers going all the time,
里面会有两到三台打印机同时工作
it was a pretty noisy place.
声音异常嘈杂
Okay,so let's see,what else I was going to say about the printer...
让我想想接下来要介绍打印机的哪个方面
What is it? The 238...
是多少？是238吗？
328,so I think.
我记得是328
This saw...this confused to the 328 and the logic behind that is then to use...
它计算到2的328次方 刚才我记混了 至于为什么是这样
This only has 132 print positions.
这是因为它只有132个打印位（即只能打印132列）
【据此可知他们采用的是3型的1403打印机】
And that's 2 to the 238.
那恰好是2的平方到2的238次方
Paul:328. Ken:328.
Paul：是328次方！ Ken：抱歉 是328次方
So the last part of the demo is that...let's talk about the tape drive.
在演示的最后 让我们来介绍一下磁带机
You want...yeah I'll start it up...you want to go.
你来……我来把它打开……还是你来吧
Okay you want to start it and talk...
你把它们打开然后讲解一下
Now the tape that you're seeing spinning here is...it's mylar tape.
你们看到的在这里转动的是聚酯薄膜磁带
Remember the old VCRs?
还记得老式的盒式磁带录像机吗？
This tape is very similar what was in your VCRs.
这里的磁带和你录像机里的磁带非常类似
Now,on your VCR,the way it worked...is...move reel-to-reel.
在录像机中 磁带从一个轮转移到另一个轮上
So one reel turn and it pulled the tape across.
一个轮子转动 就能把磁带拉过去
However,on this machine,we want to start it and stop it very very quickly.
然而我们希望非常快速地启动和停止这台机器
And if we were to do that reel-to-reel,there just be too much momentum.
如果磁带只是直接从一个轮卷绕到另一个轮的话 磁带体的动量太大了
So it end up stretching the tape.
结果就是容易把磁带拉长 拉坏
So,we had this way of buffering the tape.
因此我们要使用一种缓冲磁带运动的办法
There's a motor...here that is pulling the tape across the read/write head.
这里是电机 它把磁带牵引通过读/写磁头
But it's pulling on free tape.
但电机只会牵拉能自由运动的磁带
Now what's happening is we have vacuum columns here.
我们看到在这儿有两个真空竖槽
And the vacuum is sucking the tape down.
真空会把磁带体向下吸
And you see there's a hole at the top, and a hole at the bottom.
可以发现上面这里有个小孔 底下也有一个
But when the tape crosses one of those holes,
当检测到磁带通过小孔的位置时
it tells this reel to either feed or take up,
就会给转轮发送输带或收带的信号
depending on which hole is covered.
具体取决于遮挡的是哪个小孔
So that's the way we get this to operate in this manner.
这就是机器的工作方式了
Now another thing about this is that when the job is done,
初次之外 当磁带读写工作完成后
you want to be able to quickly unload the tape.
我们希望能够快速地卸载磁带
And so that means we need to do what's called a "high-speed rewind".
这时我们要进行“高速倒带”的操作
And I'm going to demonstrate that.
我现在演示一下
Now these are doing very high-speed rewinds.
现在机器正在进行所谓的“高速倒带”
However we don't want to go at that same speed all the way off to the end of the reel.
然而我们也不能让它以相同的速度倒带到结束
So at some point it's going to stop,and go into a slow-speed rewind.
所以到达快要停止的某个位置时 就会自动进入“低速倒带”模式
Now one more thing about this tape,sometimes operators make mistakes.
还有一点要提 有时操作员会犯错
Let's suppose you had a very valuable Read-Tape,
现在你有一盘及其珍贵的只用来读取的磁带
had your data on it and then it was writing to another tape.
上面保存有数据 可以写到另一盘磁带上
Well sometimes,the operator might make a mistake.
有时 操作员犯了个迷糊
He put your valuable tape on the drive that's going to be writing.
他把这珍贵的磁带装在了一台即将进行写入操作的磁带机上
So,there's a way of protecting yourself.
这时我们有一种保护策略
There's this ring in here,called the "right ring".
这里有一个圆环 叫做“权限环”
So...No ring,no right.
也就是说没有环 就没有权限（写入）
So if the operator happens to mount on the wrong drive,you're safe.
这样哪怕是操作员把它装载到错误的磁带机上 数据也是安全的
So,very very good idea.
这是一个非常棒的设计
Another interesting thing about tapes in the era.
那时的磁带还有一个有意思的地方
IBM advises their customers when you're creating a valuable tape,make two copies of it.
IBM建议他们的用户 制作珍贵磁带的同时为其制作两份拷贝
Why would they do that?
为什么要这样做呢？
Backup.And why two backups?
当然是为了备份 可为什么要做两份备份呢？
One backup you keep on site and another backup you keep off site.
这是因为其中一份作为现场备份 另一份存放在异地
And today we probably backup to the cloud.
如今我们通常将数据备份到云端
Hopefully at the other end of the cloud,they're doing something like those too.
但愿在云端的数据中心 他们也为你做了这样的双重备份
Hopefully...The last thing I'd say about this and the right rings and the tape,
也许吧……在介绍完磁带的双重备份和“权限环”后 我还想说
that when you were running a job,when you were running payroll,
当你在从事像制作工资名单这样的工作的时候
there was a lot of different steps,a lot of manual intervention, a lot of operator instructions.
你要分好几步来做 还要做很多人工干预 很多操作员指令
So when you wrote a payroll system,you wrote a number of programs,
当你设计制作工资名单系统的同时 不仅要编写程序
but you also wrote a run book that was could be pretty thick,with flowcharts.
还要写一本厚厚的带有流程图的运行手册
It said mount this tape,punched these cards,dismount the tape,mount another tape...
里面指示操作员装载磁带，给卡片打孔，卸载磁带后装载另一盘磁带等等
So,one of the things that you saw with a high-speed rewind was
你刚才所见到的“高速倒带”的优势之一就是
it made the computer operation more efficient.
它能使得计算机的操作更加高效
Because it could...you could rewind the tape really fast,take it off and another tape.
这样你就能快速地倒回磁带 卸下并换上另一盘磁带了
There was a lot of that went on,and of course a lot of errors that went on.
当然这样的设计有利也有弊 它经常发生问题
So,I think that's sort of the end of the formal demo.
大概正式的讲解和演示就到这里了
Those couple of little...
这几个小的……
Go ahead...
你先继续说……
If you put your cards on tape,
如果你将穿孔卡片的数据转储到磁带上的话
there's a way you can sort using tape.
我们有通过磁带进行数据分类排序的方法
And you can sort fifty times faster than you can with that machine.
这样分类比你用那台机器对卡片进行分类要快五十倍
So that was another good reason to buy these machines.
这是购买磁带机的另一个极好的理由
Another interesting fact is you've probably all got these in your pockets.
还有一个有趣的事实 大家口袋里都装着这个吧
How much power do you take,anybody know?
有人知道它的功率有多大吗？
About one Watt.
大概1瓦
How much power do you think this machine takes?
那你觉得这台机器的功率有多大呢？
When it's fully operational,twelve thousand Watts!
当它全力运转的时候有12000瓦！
We've got two of them in this room,twenty four thousand Watts.
我们这个房间里有两台 也就是24000瓦
So some people say we turn them both on,the lights in Mountain View dim a little.
因此有人说当我们把它们都打开的时候 连山景城的灯光都会变暗一点呢！
Ha ha ha! Okay.
哈哈哈！那就到这里吧